There's a poem written
هناك قصيدة مكتوبة
by a very famous English poet
من قبل شاعر انجليزي مشهور جداً
at the end of the 19th century.
في نهاية القرن 19.
It was said to echo in Churchill's brain
قيل أنها كان لها صدى في دماغ تشرشل
in the 1930s.
في الثلاثنيات.
And the poem goes:
والقصيدة تقول :
"On the idle hill of summer,
"على تلة الصيف الخاملة،
lazy with the flow of streams,
متكاسلة بمرور التيارات،
hark I hear a distant drummer,
أصغي، فأسمع طبالا بعيدا،
drumming like a sound in dreams,
يقرع الطبل كصوت في الأحلام،
far and near and low and louder on the roads of earth go by,
بعيدا وقريبا ومنخفضة وصاخبة تسير على طرق الأرض،
dear to friend and food to powder,
عزيزة على صديق وغذاء لمسحوق،
soldiers marching,
الجنود يمشون،
soon to die."
قريبا ليموتوا."
Those who are interested in poetry,
أولئك الذين هم مهتمون بالشعر،
the poem is "A Shropshire Lad" written by A.E. Housman.
القصيدة هي "A Shropshire Lad" كتبها آلفرد إدوارد هاوسمان.
But what Housman understood,
ولكن ما فهمه هاوسمان،
and you hear it in the symphonies of Nielsen too,
وتسمعونه في سمفونية نيلسون كذلك،
was that the long, hot, silvan summers
كان أن صيف سيلفان الحار والطويل
of stability of the 19th century
من الاستقرار في القرن 19
were coming to a close,
وصل الى نهايته،
and that we were about to move
وكنا على وشك الانتقال
into one of those terrifying periods of history
إلى أحد تلك الفترات المُرعبة في التاريخ
when power changes.
عندما تتغير السلطة.
And these are always periods, ladies and gentlemen,
وهذه هي دائما فترات، أيها السيدات والسادة،
accompanied by turbulence,
مصحوبة باضطراب،
and all too often by blood.
وغالبا بالدم.
And my message for you
ورسالتي لكم
is that I believe we are condemned, if you like,
أعتقد أنه محكوم علينا، إذا شئتم،
to live at just one of those moments in history
أن نعيش واحدة من تلك اللحظات في التاريخ
when the gimbals upon which
حين تكون المرتكز الذي عليه
the established order of power is beginning to change
بدأ النظام المؤسس للسلطة في التغير
and the new look of the world,
والشكل الجديد للعالم،
the new powers that exist in the world,
القوى الجديدة الموجودة في العالم،
are beginning to take form.
بدأت بالتشكل.
And these are -- and we see it very clearly today --
وهؤلاء هم -- ونحن نرى ذلك واضحا جدا اليوم --
nearly always highly turbulent times, highly difficult times,
دائما تقريبا أوقات مضطربة للغاية، أوقات صعبة للغاية،
and all too often very bloody times.
وفي مرات كثيرة أوقات دامية جدا.
By the way, it happens about once every century.
وبالمناسبة ، إنها تحدث تقريباً مرة كل قرن.
You might argue that the last time it happened --
قد تقولون بأن آخر مرة حدث ذلك --
and that's what Housman felt coming and what Churchill felt too --
وهذا ما أحس به هاوسمان قادما وما أحس به تشرشل كذلك --
was that when power passed from the old nations,
أنه حين تم تمرير السلطة من الأمم القديمة
the old powers of Europe,
السلط القديمة في أوروبا،
across the Atlantic to the new emerging power
على امتداد المحيط الأطلسي للقوة الجديدة الناشئة
of the United States of America --
للولايات المتحدة الأمريكية --
the beginning of the American century.
بداية القرن الأمريكي.
And of course, into the vacuum
وبالطبع، في الفراغ
where the too-old European powers used to be
حيث كانت توجد السلط الأوروبية العريقة
were played the two bloody catastrophes
قد وقعت الكارثتان الدمويتان
of the last century --
في القرن الماضي --
the one in the first part and the one in the second part: the two great World Wars.
واحدة في الجزء الأول وواحدة في الجزء الثاني: الحربان العالميتان الكبريان.
Mao Zedong used to refer to them as the European civil wars,
ماو تسي تونغ اعتاد أن يصفهما على أنهما الحربان الأهليتان الأوروبيتان،
and it's probably a more accurate way of describing them.
وذلك على الأرجح الأكثر دقة في وصفهم.
Well, ladies and gentlemen,
حسنا ، أيها السيدات والسادة ،
we live at one of those times.
نحن نعيش في واحد من هذه الأوقات.
But for us, I want to talk about three factors today.
ولكن بالنسبة لنا، أريد التحدث عن ثلاثة عوامل اليوم.
And the first of these, the first two of these,
وأولها، أو الأولى والثانية منها،
is about a shift in power.
هي حول التحول في السلطة.
And the second is about some new dimension which I want to refer to,
والثاني حول بعد جديد أود أن أشير إليه،
which has never quite happened in the way it's happening now.
والذي حدث تقريبا بنفس الصورة التي تحدث الآن.
But let's talk about the shifts of power that are occurring to the world.
ولكن دعونا نتحدث عن تحولات السلطة التي تحدث في العالم.
And what is happening today
وما يحدث اليوم
is, in one sense, frightening
هو، بشكل ما ، مخيف
because it's never happened before.
لأنه لم يحدث أبدا من قبل.
We have seen lateral shifts of power --
وقد شهدنا تحولات جانبية للسلطة --
the power of Greece passed to Rome
تمرير السلطة من اليونان إلى روما
and the power shifts that occurred
وتحولات السلطة التي حصلت
during the European civilizations --
خلال الحضارات الأوروبية --
but we are seeing something slightly different.
ولكن بدأنا نرى شيئا مختلفا قليلا.
For power is not just moving laterally
بسبب أن السلطة لا تتحرك فقط جانبيا
from nation to nation.
من أمة إلى أمة.
It's also moving vertically.
إنها تتحرك أيضا عموديا.
What's happening today is that the power that was encased,
ما يحدث اليوم هو أن السلطة التي كانت مغطاة،
held to accountability, held to the rule of law,
تقع تحت المساءلة وتحت سيادة القانون،
within the institution of the nation state
داخل مؤسسة الدولة القومية
has now migrated in very large measure onto the global stage.
قد هاجرت الآن بشكل كبير جدا إلى الساحة العالمية.
The globalization of power --
عولمة السلطة --
we talk about the globalization of markets,
نتحدث عن عولمة الأسواق،
but actually it's the globalization of real power.
لكنّها في الحقيقة عولمة السلطة الحقيقية.
And where, at the nation state level
بينما على مستوى الدولة القومية
that power is held to accountability
تقع هذه السلطة تحت المساءلة
subject to the rule of law,
و تخضع لسيادة القانون،
on the international stage it is not.
هي ليست كذلك على الساحة الدولية .
The international stage and the global stage where power now resides:
الساحة الدولية والساحة العالمية حيث السلطة تكمن الآن في:
the power of the Internet, the power of the satellite broadcasters,
سلطة الإنترنت، وسلطة محطات البث الفضائي،
the power of the money changers --
سلطة الصرافين --
this vast money-go-round
والأموال الهائلة المتجولة
that circulates now 32 times the amount of money necessary
التي تدور الآن هي 32 ضعف المبلغ اللازم
for the trade it's supposed to be there to finance --
للتجارة أنه من المفترض أن تكون هناك لتمويل --
the money changers, if you like,
والصرافون، ان شئتم،
the financial speculators
المضاربون الماليون
that have brought us all to our knees quite recently,
التي دفعتنا جميعا مؤخرا للخنوع،
the power of the multinational corporations
سلطة الشركات المتعددة الجنسيات
now developing budgets
تراكم الآن ميزانيات
often bigger than medium-sized countries.
في كثير من الأحيان أكبر من البلدان المتوسطة الحجم.
These live in a global space
هؤلاء يعيشون في فضاء عالمي
which is largely unregulated,
والذي هو غير منظم بشكل كبير،
not subject to the rule of law,
لا تخضع لسيادة القانون،
and in which people may act free of constraint.
وفيها قد يتصرف الناس بحرية من كل القيود.
Now that suits the powerful
الآن هذا يلائم القوي
up to a moment.
حتى هذه اللحظة.
It's always suitable for those who have the most power
انها دائما مناسبة لأولئك الذين لديهم السلطة أكثر
to operate in spaces without constraint,
للعمل في الأماكن دون قيود،
but the lesson of history is that, sooner or later,
لكن الدرس المستفاد من التاريخ هو أنه، عاجلا أو آجلا،
unregulated space --
الفضاء الغير منظم --
space not subject to the rule of law --
فضاء لا يخضع لسيادة القانون --
becomes populated, not just by the things you wanted --
أصبح مأهولا، ليس فقط بالأشياء التي تريد --
international trade, the Internet, etc. --
التجارة الدولية، الأنترنيت، وما إلى ذلك --
but also by the things you don't want --
ولكن أيضا بالأشياء التي لا تريد --
international criminality, international terrorism.
الإجرام الدولي والإرهاب الدولي.
The revelation of 9/11
وحي ال 9/11
is that even if you are the most powerful nation on earth,
حتى لو كنت أقوى دولة على وجه الأرض،
nevertheless,
مع ذلك،
those who inhabit that space can attack you
يمكن لهؤلاء الذين يقطنون تلك المساحة الهجوم عليك
even in your most iconic of cities
حتى في معظم مدنكم المميزة
one bright September morning.
في صباح أحد أيام سبتمبر المشرقة.
It's said that something like 60 percent
قيل إن شيئا مثل 60 في المئة
of the four million dollars that was taken to fund 9/11
من الأربعة ملايين دولار التي تم اتخاذها لتمويل 9/11
actually passed through the institutions of the Twin Towers
مرت في الواقع من خلال المؤسسات الدستورية في برجي مركز التجارة العالمي
which 9/11 destroyed.
والتي دمرتها 9/11 .
You see, our enemies also use this space --
ترون، أعدائنا أيضا استخدموا هذه المساحة --
the space of mass travel, the Internet, satellite broadcasters --
مساحة السفر ، والإنترنت، محطات البث الفضائي --
to be able to get around their poison,
ليكونوا قادرين على الالتفاف بسمومهم،
which is about destroying our systems and our ways.
وهي عبارة عن تدمير أنظمتنا وطرقنا.
Sooner or later,
عاجلا أم آجلا،
the rule of history
قانون التاريخ
is that where power goes
أنه عندما تذهب السلطة
governance must follow.
يجب أن يتبعها الحكم.
And if it is therefore the case, as I believe it is,
وإذا كان ذلك هو الحال، وأعتقد أنه كذلك ،
that one of the phenomenon of our time
إن واحدة من هذه الظواهر في عصرنا
is the globalization of power,
هي عولمة السلطة،
then it follows that one of the challenges of our time
ثم يتبع ذلك أن واحدا من التحديات في عصرنا
is to bring governance to the global space.
هو جعل الحكم في الفضاء العالمي.
And I believe that the decades ahead of us now
وأعتقد أن العقود التي تنتظرنا الآن
will be to a greater or lesser extent turbulent
وسوف يكون إلى حد أكبر أو أقل اضطرابا
the more or less we are able to achieve that aim:
أكثر أو أقل ونحن قادرون على تحقيق ذلك الهدف:
to bring governance to the global space.
لجلب الحكم إلى الفضاء العالمي.
Now notice, I'm not talking about government.
لاحظوا الآن، أنا لا أتحدث عن الحكومة.
I'm not talking about setting up
أنا لا أتحدث عن إنشاء
some global democratic institution.
بعض المؤسسات العالمية الديمقراطية.
My own view, by the way, ladies and gentlemen,
وجهة نظري الخاصة، بالمناسبة، أيها السيدات والسادة،
is that this is unlikely to be done
أنه ليس من المرجح أن يتم ذلك
by spawning more U.N. institutions.
بواسطة تفريخ المزيد من المؤسسات التابعة للامم المتحدة.
If we didn't have the U.N., we'd have to invent it.
إذا لم يكن لدينا في الأمم المتحدة، سوف يترتب علينا أن نوجدها.
The world needs an international forum.
يحتاج العالم إلى محفل دولي.
It needs a means by which you can legitimize international action.
إنها تحتاج الى الوسائل التي يمكنها إضفاء الشرعية على العمل الدولي.
But when it comes to governance of the global space,
ولكن عندما يأتي إلى الحكم من الفضاء العالمي،
my guess is this won't happen
تقديري هو أن هذا لن يحدث
through the creation of more U.N. institutions.
من خلال إنشاء المزيد من المؤسسات التابعة للامم المتحدة.
It will actually happen by the powerful coming together
هذا لن يحدث في الواقع بتجمع الأقوياء معا
and making treaty-based systems,
وخلق أنظمة قائمة على المعاهدات،
treaty-based agreements,
الاتفاقيات القائمة على المعاهدات،
to govern that global space.
لحكم الفضاء العالمي.
And if you look, you can see them happening, already beginning to emerge.
وإذا نظرت، يمكنكم أن تروها تقع، بدأت بالفعل في الظهور.
The World Trade Organization: treaty-based organization,
منظمة التجارة العالمية: منظمة قائمة على المعاهدات،
entirely treaty-based,
مستندة بالكامل على المعاهدات،
and yet, powerful enough to hold even the most powerful, the United States,
وحتى الآن، قوية بما يكفي لتعرّض حتى الاقوى، الولايات المتحدة،
to account if necessary.
إلى الحساب إذا لزم الأمر.
Kyoto: the beginnings of struggling to create
إتفاقية كيوتو: بدايات الكفاح من أجل خلق
a treaty-based organization.
منظمة معتمدة على المعاهدات.
The G20:
مجموعة العشرون
we know now that we have to put together an institution
ونحن نعلم الآن أن علينا أن نضع معا مؤسسة
which is capable of bringing governance
تكون قادرة على تحقيق الحكم
to that financial space for financial speculation.
على تلك المساحة المالية للمضاربات المالية.
And that's what the G20 is, a treaty-based institution.
وهذه هي مجموعة العشرين ، وهي مؤسسة تعتمد على معاهدات.
Now there's a problem there,
الآن هناك مشكلة في ذلك،
and we'll come back to it in a minute,
وسوف نعود إليها خلال دقيقة ،
which is that if you bring the most powerful together
وهو أنه إذا جمعت الأكثر قوة معا
to make the rules in treaty-based institutions,
لوضع القواعد في مؤسسات قائمة على معاهدات،
to fill that governance space,
لملء فضاء الحكم ذاك،
then what happens to the weak who are left out?
ثم ماذا يحدث للضعفاء الذين يتم استبعادهم؟
And that's a big problem,
وهذه مشكلة كبيرة،
and we'll return to it in just a second.
وسوف نعود إليها في ثانية فقط.
So there's my first message,
إذن تلك رسالتي الأولى،
that if you are to pass through these turbulent times
أنه إن كان عليك المرور من هذه الأوقات العصيبة
more or less turbulently,
باضطراب أقل أو أكثر،
then our success in doing that
فنجاحنا في القيام بذلك إذن
will in large measure depend on our capacity
سيعتمد بشكل كبير على قدرتنا
to bring sensible governance
على جلب الحكم الراشد
to the global space.
للفضاء العالمي.
And watch that beginning to happen.
ومراقبة حدوث تلك البداية.
My second point is,
نقطتي الثانية هي،
and I know I don't have to talk to an audience like this
وأعرف أنه ليس علي الحديث لجمهور كهذا
about such a thing,
بخصوص هذا الأمر،
but power is not just shifting vertically,
لكن السلطة لا تتحول فقط عموديا،
it's also shifting horizontally.
إنها تتحول أفقيا كذلك.
You might argue that the story, the history of civilizations,
قد تجادلون أن القصة، تاريخ الحضارات،
has been civilizations gathered around seas --
قد كان حضارات متجمعة حول البحار --
with the first ones around the Mediterranean,
بكون الأولى حول البحر الأبيض المتوسط،
the more recent ones in the ascendents of Western power around the Atlantic.
واللاحقة في أسلاف السلطة الغربية حول المحيط الأطلسي.
Well it seems to me
حسنا يبدو لي
that we're now seeing a fundamental shift of power, broadly speaking,
أننا نرى الآن تحولا جوهريا للسلطة، بشكل عام،
away from nations gathered around the Atlantic [seaboard]
بعيدا عن الأمم المجتمعة حول المحيط الأطلسي [ساحل البحر]
to the nations gathered around the Pacific rim.
إلى الأمم التي تجتمع حول المحيط الهادئ.
Now that begins with economic power,
الآن هذا يبدأ بسلطة اقتصادية،
but that's the way it always begins.
لكن هكذا يبدأ الأمر دائما.
You already begin to see the development of foreign policies,
بالفعل بدأتم رؤية رؤية تطور السياسات الأجنبية،
the augmentation of military budgets
زيادة الميزانيات العسكرية
occurring in the other growing powers in the world.
التي تحدث في القوى الأخرى الناشئة في العالم.
I think actually
أعتقد في الواقع
this is not so much a shift from the West to the East;
هذا ليس حقيقة تحولا من الغرب إلى الشرق؛
something different is happening.
شيء مختلف يحدث.
My guess is, for what it's worth,
تخميني هو، على قدر ما يستحق،
is that the United States will remain
هو أن الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية ستبقى
the most powerful nation on earth
أقوى أمة على الأرض
for the next 10 years, 15,
لل10 وال15 سنة المقبلة،
but the context in which she holds her power
لكن السياق التي تتمسك فيه بالسلطة
has now radically altered; it has radically changed.
قد تغير بشكل جذري؛ قد تغير بشكل جذري.
We are coming out of 50 years,
نحن خارجون من 50 سنة،
most unusual years, of history
أكثر السنوات غرابة في التاريخ
in which we have had a totally mono-polar world,
حيث كان لدينا عالم أحادي القطبية بالكامل،
in which every compass needle
تشير فيه كل ابرة بوصلة
for or against
مع أو ضد
has to be referenced by its position to Washington --
عليها أن يكون مشار إليها بوضعها بالنسبة لواشنطن --
a world bestrode by a single colossus.
عالم تتم قيادته بتمثال ضخم.
But that's not a usual case in history.
لكن ذلك ليس حالة اعتيادية في التاريخ.
In fact, what's now emerging
في الواقع، ما ينبثق الآن
is the much more normal case of history.
هو الحالة الأكثر اعتيادية في التاريخ.
You're beginning to see the emergence
تبدأون برؤية انبثاق
of a multi-polar world.
عالم متعدد الأقطاب.
Up until now,
لحد الآن،
the United States has been the dominant feature of our world.
الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية كانت السمة الغالبة على عالمنا.
They will remain the most powerful nation,
ستبقى أقوى أمة،
but they will be the most powerful nation
لكنهم سيكونوا أقوى أمة
in an increasingly multi-polar world.
في عالم متعدد الأقطاب باضطراد.
And you begin to see the alternative centers of power building up --
وتبدأ في رؤية مراكز القوة البديلة تنبني --
in China, of course,
في الصين، بالطبع،
though my own guess is that China's ascent to greatness is not smooth.
لكن تخميني الخاص هو أن صعود الصين إلى العظمة ليس سلسا.
It's going to be quite grumpy
سيكون غاضبا جدا
as China begins to democratize her society
ببدء الصين في دمقرطة مجتمعها
after liberalizing her economy.
بعد تحرير اقتصادها.
But that's a subject of a different discussion.
لكن ذلك موضوع لنقاش آخر.
You see India, you see Brazil.
ترون في الهند، ترون في البرازيل.
You see increasingly
ترون على نحو متزايد
that the world now looks actually, for us Europeans,
أن العالم يبدو في الواقع الآن، بالنسبة لنا نحن الآوروبيون،
much more like Europe in the 19th century.
كثيرا مثل أوروبا في القرن 19.
Europe in the 19th century:
أوروبا في القرن 19:
a great British foreign secretary, Lord Canning,
وزارة خارجية بريطانية عظيمة، اللورد كانينغ،
used to describe it as the "European concert of powers."
اعتاد على وصفها على أنها "مهرجان أوروبا للقوى."
There was a balance, a five-sided balance.
كان هناك توازن، توازن من خمس جوانب.
Britain always played to the balance.
بريطانيا كانت دائما تلعب بتوازن.
If Paris got together with Berlin,
إن انضمت باريس إلى برلين،
Britain got together with Vienna and Rome to provide a counterbalance.
بريطانيا ستنضم إلى فيينا وروما لإحداث توازن مضاد.
Now notice,
لاحظوا الآن،
in a period which is dominated by a mono-polar world,
في مرحلة هيمن عليها عالم أحادي القطبية،
you have fixed alliances --
هناك تحالفات ثابتة --
NATO, the Warsaw Pact.
الناتو وحلف وارسو.
A fixed polarity of power
قطبية ثابتة من السلطة
means fixed alliances.
تعني تحالفات ثابتة.
But a multiple polarity of power
لكن تعدد قطبية السلطة
means shifting and changing alliances.
يعني تحالفات متحولة ومتغيرة.
And that's the world we're coming into,
وهذا هو العالم الذي نحن مقدمون عليه،
in which we will increasingly see
حيث سنرى بتزايد
that our alliances are not fixed.
أن تحالفاتنا ثابتة.
Canning, the great British foreign secretary once said,
كانينغ، وزير الخارجية البريطاني العظيم قال من قبل،
"Britain has a common interest,
"بريطانيا لها مصالح مشتركة،
but no common allies."
لكن ليس لها تحالف واحد."
And we will see increasingly
وسنرى بتزايد
that even we in the West
أنه حتى نحن في الغرب
will reach out, have to reach out,
سنمد يدنا، سيكون علينا أن نمد يدنا،
beyond the cozy circle of the Atlantic powers
ما وراء دائرة القوى الأطلسية المريحة
to make alliances with others
للتحالف مع الآخرين
if we want to get things done in the world.
إن أردنا إنجاز أمور في هذا العالم.
Note, that when we went into Libya,
لاحظوا أنه حين ذهبنا إلى ليبيا،
it was not good enough for the West to do it alone;
لم يكن من الجيد للغرب أن يقوم بذلك لوحده؛
we had to bring others in.
كان علينا إحضار آخرين.
We had to bring, in this case, the Arab League in.
كان علينا إحضار، في هذه الحالة، جامعة الدول العربية.
My guess is Iraq and Afghanistan are the last times
تخميني أن العراق وأفغانستان هي المرتان الأخيرتان
when the West has tried to do it themselves,
حيث يحاول الغرب القيام بالأمور بذاته،
and we haven't succeeded.
ولم ننجح.
My guess
تخميني
is that we're reaching the beginning of the end of 400 years --
أننا وصلنا إلى بداية نهاية 400 سنة --
I say 400 years because it's the end of the Ottoman Empire --
أقول 400 سنة لأنها نهاية الإمبراطورية العثمانية --
of the hegemony of Western power,
لسيطرة القوى الغربية،
Western institutions and Western values.
المؤسسات الغربية والقيم الغربية.
You know, up until now, if the West got its act together,
تعرفون، لحد الآن، إن نظم الغرب ذاته،
it could propose and dispose
سيقترح ويصرف
in every corner of the world.
في كل ركن من العالم.
But that's no longer true.
لكن ذلك لم يعد صحيحا.
Take the last financial crisis
خذوا الأزمة الإقتصادية الأخيرة
after the Second World War.
بعد الحرب العالمية الثانية.
The West got together --
اتحد الغرب --
the Bretton Woods Institution, World Bank, International Monetary Fund --
مؤسسة بريتون وودز، البنك الدولي، صندوق النقد الدولي --
the problem solved.
تم حل المشكل.
Now we have to call in others.
علينا الآن أن ندعو الآخرين.
Now we have to create the G20.
علينا الآن إنشاء مجموعة العشرين.
Now we have to reach beyond the cozy circle
علينا الآن أن نصل ما هو أبعد من الدائرة المريحة
of our Western friends.
لأصدقائنا الغربيين.
Let me make a prediction for you,
دعوني أتنبأ لكم بأمر،
which is probably even more startling.
هو على الأرجح أكثر إذهالا حتى.
I suspect we are now reaching the end
أشك في أننا الآن نصل إلى نهاية
of 400 years
ال400 سنة
when Western power was enough.
حين كانت القوى الغربية كافية.
People say to me, "The Chinese, of course,
يقول لي الناس، "الصين بالطبع
they'll never get themselves involved
لن يشركوا أنفسهم أبدا
in peace-making, multilateral peace-making around the world."
في صنع السلام، في صنع السلام المتعدد الأطراف حول العالم."
Oh yes? Why not?
أوه نعم؟ لم لا؟
How many Chinese troops
كم عدد القوات الصينية
are serving under the blue beret, serving under the blue flag,
التي تعمل بقبعات زرقاء، تحت الراية الزرقاء،
serving under the U.N. command in the world today?
يعملون تحت إمرة الأمم المتحدة في العالم اليوم؟
3,700.
3,700.
How many Americans? 11.
كم عدد الأمريكيين؟ 11.
What is the largest naval contingent
ما هي أكبر وحدة بحرية
tackling the issue of Somali pirates?
تعالج مشكلة القراصنة الصوماليين؟
The Chinese naval contingent.
الوحدة البحرية الصينية.
Of course they are, they are a mercantilist nation.
بالطبع هي كذلك، إنها أمم تجارية بحتة.
They want to keep the sea lanes open.
تريد أن تترك الممرات البحرية مفتوحة.
Increasingly, we are going to have to do business
علينا القيام بالأعمال بتزايد
with people with whom we do not share values,
مع أشخاص لا نشاركهم قيمهم،
but with whom, for the moment, we share common interests.
لكننا نشاركهم مصلحة مشتركة الآن.
It's a whole new different way
إنها طريقة كاملة جديدة
of looking at the world that is now emerging.
للنظر إلى عالم ينبثق الآن.
And here's the third factor,
وها هنا العامل الثالث،
which is totally different.
والذي هو مختلف تماما.
Today in our modern world,
اليوم في عالمنا المتحضر،
because of the Internet,
بسبب الأنترنيت،
because of the kinds of things people have been talking about here,
بسبب أصناف الأشخاص الذين تم الحديث عنهم هنا،
everything is connected to everything.
كل شيء مرتبط بكل شيء.
We are now interdependent.
نحن الآن مترابطون.
We are now interlocked,
نحن الآن متشابكون،
as nations, as individuals,
كأمم، كأفراد،
in a way which has never been the case before,
بطريقة لم تحدث قط من قبل،
never been the case before.
لم تحدث قط من قبل.
The interrelationship of nations,
العلاقات المتبادلة بين الأمم،
well it's always existed.
حسنا الأمر دائما مثير للاهتمام.
Diplomacy is about managing the interrelationship of nations.
الديبلوماسية هي إدارة العلاقات المتبادلة بين الأمم.
But now we are intimately locked together.
لكننا الآن مقفلون باحكام معا.
You get swine flu in Mexico,
تصاب بانفلونزا الخنازير في المكسيك،
it's a problem for Charles de Gaulle Airport
فيصبح مشكلا في مطار شارل ديغول
24 hours later.
بعد 24 ساعة.
Lehman Brothers goes down, the whole lot collapses.
يسقط ليمان براذرز، فينهار كل شيء.
There are fires in the steppes of Russia,
تشتعل نيران في سهول روسيا،
food riots in Africa.
أعمال شغب بسبب الغذاء في أفريقيا.
We are all now deeply, deeply, deeply interconnected.
نحن الآن جميعا، مرتبطون بعمق كبير جدا.
And what that means
وما يعنيه ذلك
is the idea of a nation state acting alone,
هو فكرة دولة وطنية بمفردها،
not connected with others,
ليست مرتبطة مع الآخرين،
not working with others,
لا تعمل مع الآخرين،
is no longer a viable proposition.
لم يعد اقتراحا مجديا.
Because the actions of a nation state
لأن أفعال دولة وطنية
are neither confined to itself,
لا تقتصر لا على ذاتها،
nor is it sufficient for the nation state itself
ولا هي كافية للدولة الوطنية بذاتها
to control its own territory,
للتحكم في أراضيها،
because the effects outside the nation state
لأن التأثيرات خارج الدولة الوطنية
are now beginning to affect what happens inside them.
بدأت الآن في التأثير على ما يحدث داخلها.
I was a young soldier
كنت جنديا شابا
in the last of the small empire wars of Britain.
في آخر ما بقي من امبراطورية بريطانيا الحربية.
At that time, the defense of my country
في ذلك الوقت، دفاع دولتي
was about one thing and one thing only:
كان يتعلق بأمر واحد وأمر واحد فقط:
how strong was our army, how strong was our air force,
مدى قوة جيشنا، ومدة قوة قواتنا الجوية،
how strong was our navy and how strong were our allies.
مدى قوة بحريتنا ومدى قوة حلفائنا.
That was when the enemy was outside the walls.
ذلك كان حين كان العدو خارج جدراننا.
Now the enemy is inside the walls.
الآن العدو موجود داخل جدراننا.
Now if I want to talk about the defense of my country,
إن كان على الحديث عن دفاع دولتي الآن،
I have to speak to the Minister of Health
علي الحديث إلى وزارة الصحة
because pandemic disease is a threat to my security,
لأن الوباء المرضي تهديد للأمن،
I have to speak to the Minister of Agriculture
علي الحديث لوزارة الزراعة
because food security is a threat to my security,
لأن الأمن الغذائي تهديد للأمن،
I have to speak to the Minister of Industry
علي الحديث إلى وزارة الصناعة
because the fragility of our hi-tech infrastructure
لأن هشاشة البنية التحتية ذات التكنولوجيا العالية
is now a point of attack for our enemies --
هي الآن نقطة هجوم لأعدائنا --
as we see from cyber warfare --
كما نرى في حرب الفضاء الإلكتروني --
I have to speak to the Minister of Home Affairs
علي الحديث إلى وزارة الشؤون الداخلية
because who has entered my country,
لأن من قد دخل دولتي،
who lives in that terraced house in that inner city
والذي يعيش في ذلك المنزل المدرج في تلك المدينة الداخلية
has a direct effect on what happens in my country --
لديه تأثير مباشر على ما يحدث في دولتي --
as we in London saw in the 7/7 bombings.
كما قد رأينا نحن في لندن تفجيرات 7/7.
It's no longer the case that the security of a country
لم يعد أمن دولة
is simply a matter for its soldiers and its ministry of defense.
ببساطة مسألة تهم جنودها ووزارة دفاعها.
It's its capacity to lock together its institutions.
إنها قدرتها على تأمين مؤسساتها معا.
And this tells you something very important.
وهذا يخبرنا بشيء في غاية الأهمية.
It tells you that, in fact,
يخبرنا أنه في الواقع
our governments, vertically constructed,
حكومتنا، العمودية البنية،
constructed on the economic model of the Industrial Revolution --
مبنية على نموذج إقتصادي للثورة الصناعية --
vertical hierarchy, specialization of tasks,
تسلس هرمي رأسي، تخصص في المهام،
command structures --
هياكل قيادية --
have got the wrong structures completely.
لديهم بنيات خاطئة بالكامل.
You in business know
أنتم في مجال الإقتصاد تعرفون
that the paradigm structure of our time, ladies and gentlemen,
أن النموذج المهيكل لأزمنتنا، سيداتي سادتي،
is the network.
هو الشبكة.
It's your capacity to network that matters,
قدرتنا على التشبيك هي ما يهم،
both within your governments and externally.
سواء داخل حكوماتنا وخارجها.
So here is Ashdown's third law.
إذن هذا هو قانون أشدون الثالث.
By the way, don't ask me about Ashdown's first law and second law
بالمناسبة، لا تسألوني عن القانون الأول والثاني لأشدون
because I haven't invented those yet;
لأنه لم يتم اختراعهما بعد؛
it always sounds better if there's a third law, doesn't it?
يبدو الأمر أحسن إن كان هناك قانون ثالث، أليس كذلك؟
Ashdown's third law is that in the modern age,
قانون أشدون الثالث هو أنه في العصر الحديث،
where everything is connected to everything,
حيث كل شيء متصل بكل شيء،
the most important thing about what you can do
الأمر الأكثر أهمية بخصوص ما يمكن القيام به
is what you can do with others.
هو ما يمكن القيام به مع الآخرين.
The most important bit about your structure --
الجزء الأكثر أهمية في بنيتنا --
whether you're a government, whether you're an army regiment,
سواء كانت حكومة أو نظاما عسكريا،
whether you're a business --
سواء كان تجارة --
is your docking points, your interconnectors,
هو نقط التحامكم وترابطكم،
your capacity to network with others.
و قدرتكم على التشبيك مع الآخرين.
You understand that in industry;
تفهمون ذلك في إطار الصناعة؛
governments don't.
الحكومات لا تفعل ذلك.
But now one final thing.
لكن الآن أمر أخير.
If it is the case, ladies and gentlemen -- and it is --
إن كان الأمر كذلك، سيداتي سادتي -- وهو كذلك --
that we are now locked together
أننا الآن مؤمّنون معا
in a way that has never been quite the same before,
بطريقة لم تكن تماما كما هي الآن من قبل،
then it's also the case that we share a destiny with each other.
ومن ثم فالأمر كذلك أننا نتشارك مع بعضنا البعض في مصير واحد.
Suddenly and for the very first time,
فجأة وللمرة الأولى،
collective defense, the thing that has dominated us
الدفاع التشاركي، الأمر الذي سيطر علينا
as the concept of securing our nations,
كمبدأ تأمين دولنا،
is no longer enough.
لم يعد كافيا.
It used to be the case
كان الأمر
that if my tribe was more powerful than their tribe, I was safe;
أنه إن كانت قبيلتي أكثر قوة من قبيلتهم، كنت آمنا؛
if my country was more powerful than their country, I was safe;
إن كانت دولتي أكثر قوة من دولتهم، كنت آمنا؛
my alliance, like NATO, was more powerful than their alliance, I was safe.
حلفائي، مثل الناتو، كانت أكثر قوة من حلفائهم، كنت آمنا.
It is no longer the case.
لم يعد الأمر كذلك.
The advent of the interconnectedness
ظهور الترابط
and of the weapons of mass destruction
وأسلحة الدمار الشامل
means that, increasingly,
يعني أنه، وبتزايد،
I share a destiny with my enemy.
أتشارك في مصيري مع عدوي.
When I was a diplomat
حين كنت ديبلوماسيا
negotiating the disarmament treaties with the Soviet Union
أفاوض في اتفاقيات نزع سلاح الإتحاد السوفياتي
in Geneva in the 1970s,
في جنيف في السبعينيات،
we succeeded because we understood
نجحنا لأننا فهمنا
we shared a destiny with them.
أننا نتشارك مصير واحد معهم.
Collective security is not enough.
الأمن الجماعي ليس كافيا.
Peace has come to Northern Ireland
جاء السلام في أيرلندا الشمالية
because both sides realized that the zero-sum game couldn't work.
لأن كلا الطرفين اقتنعوا أن لعبة مجموع الصفر لن تنجح.
They shared a destiny with their enemies.
اشتركوا في نفس مصير أعدائهم.
One of the great barriers to peace in the Middle East
أحد أكبر عوائق السلام في الشرق الأوسط
is that both sides, both Israel and, I think, the Palestinians,
هو أن كلا الطرفين، إسرائيل، على ما أعتقد، والفلسطينيين،
do not understand
لا يفهمون
that they share a collective destiny.
أنهم يتشاركون في مصير مشترك.
And so suddenly, ladies and gentlemen,
وبالتالي فجأة، سيداتي سادتي،
what has been the proposition
ما قد كان اقتراح
of visionaries and poets down the ages
الملهمين والشعراء على مر العصور
becomes something we have to take seriously
أصبح شيئا نأخذه بجدية
as a matter of public policy.
كموضوع للسياسة العامة.
I started with a poem, I'll end with one.
بدأت بقصيدة، وسأنهي بواحدة.
The great poem of John Donne's.
القصيدة العظيمة لجون دون.
"Send not for whom the bell tolls."
"لا ترسل لمن يدق لهم الجرس."
The poem is called "No Man is an Island."
القصيدة تدعى "لا أحد منا جزيرة مستقلة."
And it goes:
وتقول:
"Every man's death affected me,
"موت كل رجل أثر علي،
for I am involved in mankind,
لأنني جزء من الجنس البشري،
send not to ask
لا ترسل لتسأل
for whom the bell tolls,
من يدق لهم الجرس،
it tolls for thee."
فهو يدق لك."
For John Donne, a recommendation of morality.
بالنسبة لجون دون، توصية للأخلاق.
For us, I think,
بالنسبة لنا، أعتقد،
part of the equation for our survival.
جزء من معادلة بقاءنا.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)